Guide to the African American Miscellany, 1757-1983 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Slavery Series, 1757-1867 and undated, (1 box, 2 folders)
  - 1858 Feb. 8, Bill of sale for two slave women, from John Hunter to J. E. Calhoun, Grand Gulf
  - 1858 Mar. 2, Bill of sale for two slave women: Jane and her child, from Smith Hubbard to John Hunter
  - 1858 Dec. 30, Bill of sale for one slave girl: Mary, from James S. Miller to John M. Carson, Alexander County, N.C.
  - 1859 Mar. 11, Bill of sale for one slave woman and her four children: Susan, 30 y.o., Mary, 10 y.o., Vivey, 6 y.o., and Julia, 3 y.o., from S.S. Tompkins to John S. Smyley
  - 1859 June 7, Life insurance policies for two slaves: Nancy and Margaret, taken out by E.L. McNair of S.C., Chesterfield County, S.C., (2 documents)
  - 1859 Oct. 13, Bill of sale for three slaves: Mary, 28 y.o., and two children, from D.G. Crawford
  - 1859 Nov. 29, Letter from John Brown, prison inmate, to Mrs. George L. Strens of Boss [Boston?], Mass.
  - 1860 Jan. 4, Letter on relative prices of men, women, and children, from Dickinson Hill and Co., Richmond, [Va.?]
  - 1860 Jan. 15, Auctioneer's letter, from Pulliam and Co., Richmond, [Va.?]
  - 1860 Mar. 7, Bill of sale for one slave: Susan, from John S. Seabrook to P.S. Felder, Charleston
  - 1860 May 19, Life insurance policy for one slave: Mary, 34 y.o., taken out by Bertha Buck, Charter Oak Life Insurance Policy, Savannah [Ga.], (2 documents)
  - 1860-1861, Documents detailing the prices of Betts and Gregory slave market, list broken down by gender, age, and height, Franklin St., Richmond, [Va.?], (3 documents)
  - 1860 Nov. 30, Bill of sale for one slave: Daphney, 22 y.o., from Samuel F. Shelton to Richard Jones
  - 1860 Dec. 28, Letter detailing the dropping and unsustainable price of slaves, from Dickinson, Hill and Co., Richmond [Va.?]
  - 1861 Jan. 1, Indenture to hire slave Jenny from I.F. Torrance, Grenada, Miss.
  - 1861 Jan. 17, Bills of sale for one slave boy: Wash, and one slave girl: Jane, from Jacob Semly to G.L. Davidson, (2 documents)
  - 1862 Oct. 8, Note for rental of slave man until 25 Dec. 1863 from Joseph Trout: [Cob Mam Oly] Kees, including furnishing with clothing, $90, to [name excised], Front Royal area, Va.
  - 1862 Nov. 18, Document detailing gift of slaves to James A. Clark from Richard R. Wringley, after Wringley's death
  - 1863 Feb. 21, Bill of sale for one slave man: Lawson, 35 y.o., from A.M. Bogle to A. Carson
  - 1863 Mar. 16 - June 15, Sale bonds for runaway slaves: Stephen, George, Sherrod, Charles, and Lewis, Barren County, Ky.
  - 1863 June 15, Jailer auction of runaway slaves: George, 23 y.o., Lewis, 18 y.o., Gasper, 18 y.o., Sherrod, 16 y.o., and Charles, 28 y.o., Warren County, Ky.
  - 1863 May 11, Bill of sale for one slave boy: Charles, 16 y.o., Warren County, Ky.
  - 1863 May 11, Court documents relating to the sale of slave: Miranda, belonging to Benjamin Farmer of Murphreesborough, Tenn., Warren County, Ky.
  - 1863 June 1, Bill of sale for one slave boy: Andrew, $350, to A.H. Mahey and B.J. Mahey
  - 1863 June 8, Court documents relating to the sale of runaway slave: Henry, belonging to James Burch of Tenn., Nelson County, Ky.
  - 1863 June 8, Bill of sale for one runaway slave: Rosetta, by A.B. Dyer, Ky.
  - 1863 July 6, Document certifying the freedom of Thomas Segen, 21 y.o., 5 ft. 11 in., by Richard F. Graves, Powhatan County, [Va.]
  - 1863 Aug. 3, Court documents relating to the sale of runaway slave: John, belonging to Albert Dudley of Fayette County, Woodford County, Ky.
  - 1863 Sept. 15, Court documents relating to the sale of runaway slave: Henry, belonging to James Williams of Tenn., Madison County, Ky.
  - 1863-1864, Documents relating to the sale of a runaway slave, Jim, belonging to James Strong of Giles County Tenn, Warren County, Ky., (7 documents)
  - 1863-1864, Documents relating to the sale of a runaway slave, George, belonging to Augustus Stanley of Davidson County, Tenn., Warren County, Ky., (7 documents)
  - 1863-1864, Documents relating to the sale of a runaway slave: Amanda Adalade, belonging to Alfred Goodlon of Wilson County, Warren County, (2 documents)
  - 1863 Oct. 27, Bills of sale for two slaves: Oscar, and Harry from Stewart Buchanan to G.W. Hall, Richmond, Va., (2 documents)
  - 1864 Jan. 4, Court documents relating to the sale of runaway slave: Bob, belonging to Jacob Falk of Morgan County Ala., Woodford County, Ky.
  - 1864 Jan. 5, Court documents relating to the sale of runaway slave: Edmund, Adair County, Ky.
  - 1864 Jan. 11, Court documents relating to the sale of runaway slave: Dick, belonging to John Rizer and John S. Dixon of Louisville, Nelson County, Ky., purchased by John F. Queen for $265
  - 1864 Feb. 8, Court documents relating to the sale of runaway slave: Anthony, belonging to Peter Ideley of Adams County, Miss., Shelby County, Ky.
  - 1864 Feb. 8, Sale bond of runaway slave boy: John, by George Pollard, Hanisan County, Ky.
  - 1864 Feb. 17, Bill of sale for one slave man: Arthur, $5500, from S. Cohen to Mr. Muse, Richmond, Va.
  - 1864 Mar. 14, Court documents relating to the sale of runaway slave: George, belonging to John Anderson of Nashville, Tenn., Nelson County, Ky.
  - 1864 Apr. 1, Letter for D.P. Robb concerning court proceedings on two runaway slaves, Versailles, Ky.
  - 1864 Apr. 4, Court documents relating to sale of slave boy: Jim, from Sheriff of Adair County, Adair Co., Ky.
  - 1864 Apr. 26, June 4, Documents relating to the sale of runaway slave, Felix, belonging to William Boxdell of Tenn. Warren County, Ky., (7 documents)
  - 1864 Apr. 8, June 4, Documents relating to the sale of runaway slave, Frank, belonging to William Kimble of Davidson County, Tenn., $105.40, Warren County, Ky., (6 documents)
  - 1864 June 4, Documents relating to the sale of runaway slave: Charles, belonging to William Ramsey of Tenn., Warren County, Ky., (6 documents)
  - 1864 June 6, Documents detailing the deposit of $1435.53 for the use of the Treasurer of Ky. For three slaves, was 30 cents short. From J.H. Rose to W.J. Samuels, auditor, by J.H. Rose, Bowling Green, Ky., (2 documents)
  - 1864 June 6, Cancelled bond for one slave: John, $752.25, cancelled by court because John had disease and died, Livingston County, Ky.
  - 1864 Nov. 2, Letter from James Rose to W.L. Samuels concerning runaway slaves and Maxwell's Bond
  - 1865 Feb. 2, Order quashing sale bond of Col. C. Maxwell, Bowling Green, Ky.
  - 1865 May 6, Return of check, $145.33, regarding case of slave: Anthony
  - 1865 May 15, Receipt from William Morrison for W. Butler, $20, for advertising Jim, a runaway slave
  - 1865 May 24, Statement of public sale for runaway slave boy: M., by J.W. Cade, Livingston County, Ky.
  - 1865 May 24, Statement of public sale for two runaway slaves: William and John, Livingston County, Ky.
  - 1865 May 24, Bills of sale for two runaway slaves: Abner and John, Livingston County, Ky., (2 documents)
  - 1865 May, Bills of sale for one runaway slave: Anthony, Shelby County, Ky., (2 documents)
  - 1865 June 20, Receipts for [from the payments paid by] W. Butler, Adair County, Ky. for paying fees for runaway slave Jim
  - 1865-1866, Documents relating to the sale of two runaway slaves, Emma and Francis, belonging to Allen Butler of Crittenden County, Shelby County, Ky., (5 documents)
  - 1864-1866 Jan., Court documents relating to the sale of a runaway slave, Henry Fisher, belonging to Charles Ellis of Fayette County, Shelby County, Ky., (7 documents)
  - 1866 Jan. 6, Letter regarding disagreement on slave fees and payments from J.W. Butler, Columbia, Ky.
  - 1866 Jan. 20, Letter from J.W. Butler to W.T. Samuels, Esq., Columbia, Ky.
  - 1866 Dec. 4, Court documents relating to the sale of runaway slave: Jeremiah, to John Mathis, Livingston County, Ky.
  - 1866 Dec. 6, Letter regarding refund of purchase money for slave from James W. Cade to W.T. Samuels, Esq., Smithland, Ky.
  - 1866 Dec. 8, Letter regarding the refund of money for runaway slave John from A.V. Wood to W.J. Samuels, Cadiz, Ky.
  - 1867 June 17, Letter from A.B. Dyer to W.T. Samuels, Cadiz, Ky. regarding the credit due him from the 1863 June sale of runaway slave Rosetta.
  - 1867 July 25, Letter from A.B. Dyer to Treasurer, Cadiz, Ky., regarding payment due from sale of runaway slave Rosetta. $62.35 was enclosed.
  - 1867 June 27, Letter from C.C. Hooks to W.T. Samuels, Esq., Cadiz, Ky., regarding the statement for runaway slave Rosetta.
  - 1873 Bank Book, Freedman's Savings and Trust Company
  - 1924, Handwritten paper, Dr. Bracking, Murfeesboro, Tenn.
  - Undated, Letter to W.T. Samuels, Warren County, Ky.
  - Undated, Slave pricing sheets, (2 documents)
  - Undated, No. 1 female slave sold for $1380
  - Undated, List of names of 30 slaves
  - Undated, Amounts acquired from sales of slaves
  - Undated, List of slaves' ages, (2 documents)
  - Undated, Slave prices for individual slaves, (2 documents)
  - Oversize Material, (1 folder)
    - 1802 Jan. 22, Indenture (Oversize-box 48)
    - 1843 Oct. 14, Mortgage of personal property (S.C.)
    - 1852-1865, Three bills of sale (2 Ky., 1 S.C.)
- Civil Rights Series, 1955-1983, (1 box)
  Correspondence, pamphlets, clippings, other printed material, and one Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) button, all originating from the civil rights era.
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1930-1976
    Includes news bulletins and fundraising letters from the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, the NAACP Special Contributions Fund, the Southern Christian Leadership Conference, the Medgar Evers Fund, the Southern Poverty Law Center, the United Negro College Fund, and the Schomburg Center, with various attatched pamphlets and clippings.
    - 1930 May 23, Advertisement with handwritten note: The Son of Thunder, Rev. Dr. Johnson D.D., Bessemer, Ala. (Box 1)
    - 1960, Letter to branch presidents urging them to write protest letters to Woolworth and Kress presidents, hold mass protests and sitins in a non-violent manner in support of Greensboro protests, with instructions for non-violent action, Roy Wilkins, President, NAACP, New York, N.Y.
    - 1960, Letter to branch president Joseph A. Watkins, Flagstaff, Ariz., urging protests to support North Carolina sit-ins, stressing the national economic impact of the protests and suggesting pickett signs, from Tarea Hall Pittman, Acting Regional Secretary, NAACP West Coast, San Francisco, Calif. Includes envelope.
    - 1964, Fundraising letter from Allan Knight Chalmens, Chairman, "Committee of 100," NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, New York, N.Y.
    - 1965-1968, Fundraising letters from Paul Moore Jr., Chairman, "Committee of 100," NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, New York, NY with attached pamphlets: "Negroes Beaten in Grenada School Integration"; "Children and Schools"; "Poverty Attacks the Helpless"; "Wetumpka has Everything"; "NAACP Legal Defense Fund Aids the Poor", (7 letters, 5 pamphlets)
    - 1964 Oct., Mississippi: The Long Winter Ahead, Report from Walter L. Goldfrank of the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund Vol. II, No. 2, New York, N.Y.
    - 1965 June 4, Excerpts from an address by President Lyndon B. Johnson, Howard University, prepared by the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, New York, N.Y.
    - 1967 Mar. 11, Letter from Roy Wilkins, NAACP Special Contributions Fund, New York, N.Y. with attached clippings from the NY Times: 1966 Nov. 22, "Negro Taken Dead from Alabama Jail; 3 Report Beating," Wektumpka, Ala.; 1966 Nov. 24, "Death of Negro in Jail is Studied"; 1966 Nov. 27, "Face of Violence in the South"; 1967 Feb. 28, "Negro leader killed by blast in Natchez," Natchez, Miss.
    - 1968 Nov. 2, Letter from the Southern Christian Leadership Conference, Ralph D. Abernathy, President, and Andrew J. Young, Executive Vice President with a clipping: "Score One for the Poor" (2 copies of the letter)
    - 1970 May 25, Letter from Charles Evers, The Medgar Evers Fund, Inc., New York, N.Y. with attached clipping: 1969 June 14,The New Yorker, "The Talk of the Town"
    - 1971 July 15, Fundraising letter for Charles Evers, African American and Democratic candidate for governor of Mississippi
    - 1974 Oct. 1, 1975 Apr. 21, Letters from the NAACP. Special Contributions Fund, Roy Wilkins with attached pamphlets: "Save the Children"; "Hunger USA - 1975", (2 letters, 2 pamphlets)
    - 1974, Letter from Julian Bond, President, Montgomery, the Southern Poverty Law Center Ala. with attached clipping: "Three Men to Die in Gas Chamber" and a letter from the N.C. State Department of Corrections
    - 1976 Oct., Letter from William A. McMillan to Mr. Mattie U. Russell, United Negro College Fund with attached pamphlet: "You Do Not Get Something For Nothing"
    - 1976 Oct., Letter from Ruth J. Bruche, Co-Chairman of the Committee for the Schomburg Center with attached pamphlet: "Treasures at Risk"
  - Printed Material Subseries, 1950-1983 and undated
    Includes various pamphlets on African American life and culture, bibliographies, materials on civil rights political organizations, items relating to school integration, and newspaper clippings on these topics. Arranged in date order.
    - 1950-1956, 1957-1966, Bibliographies compiled by Mrs. Mollie H. Lee, Richard B. Harrison, Public Library, Raleigh, N.C., (3 items) (Box 1)
    - 1955, Pamphlet, Southern Historical Association, Three Views of the Segregation Decisions by William Faulkner, Benjamin E. Mays, and Cecils Sims
    - 1956 July 25, Advertisement, A Physical, Not a Spiritual Separation: Race Suicide. Ecclesiastical Edict, by E.S. Askey, Rt. No. 2, Windsor, N.C.
    - 1958 June, Pamphlet, A First Step Toward School Integration by Ann Holden, edited by Jim Peck, Alexander L. Crosby, Congress of Racial Equality (CORE)
    - 1962 Mar. 13-15, Handouts from lecture series held at Howard University in honor of Edward Franklin Frazier
    - 1965 Mar., The Negro in American History and Culture: A List of Resources for Teaching From the Urban Education Collection of the Auburn Library, Urban Theological Seminary, 3041 Broadway, New York, N.Y.
    - 1965 Oct. 21-23, Program for "Materials By and About Negroes," an Institute sponsored by The Atlanta University School of Library Service, Atlanta, Ga.
    - 1965 Oct. 21-23, Program for "The Semicentennial of The Association for the Study of Negro Life and History 1915-1965," Atlanta, Ga.
    - 1967 June 2, Newsletter, Concern for a Free South (CFS), vol. 1, no. 2
    - 1967 Feb. 13, Pamphlet, 23rd Annual E. Azalic Huckley Memorial Concert, Detroit Public Library
    - 1967, Flyer, Does your library have a copy of 'Eyewitness: The Negro in American History,' by William I. Katz?
    - 1967, Pamphlet, The Negro in America: A Selected List of Recent Books, Detroit Public Library
    - 1968 Jan. 4, Pamphlet, Recent Library of Congress Publications on Africa
    - 1968 July 22-26, Program for "Bibliographic and Other Resources for the Study of the American Negro," Howard University, Washington D.C. (2 items)
    - 1968, Flyer, American Negro Collections: A List of References, Howard University, Washington D.C.
    - 1968, Pamphlet, Proud Heritage: The Negro in America
    - 1968, Pamphlet, Golden State Mutual's Negro Art Collection
    - 1968, Brochure, Howard University Campus Guide
    - 1968 Feb., News from Southern Conference Educational Fund (SCEF), Louisville, Ky. (1968 Feb. 12 Orangeburg Massacre); February 1968 News from SCEF, Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) - Police Terror in Nashville
    - 1968 July, Editorial from McCall's Magazine, What Can One Woman Do? Includes six examples of how individuals have worked to reduce the disparities between "two societies." Includes Ann Atwater from Durham, N.C.
    - 1968 July-Aug, Magazine, Southern Education Report, A Magazine for Decision-Makers; articles: Black Militancy and its Effect on Education; Lack of African Americans on College Faculties
    - 1968 Oct. 20, Pamphlet, Readings on White Racism
    - 1968 Dec. 8, Pamphlet, NAACP Rocky Mount Branch, Annual Meeting at Mount Pisgah Church Inn
    - 1972, Flyer, Society for African Culture Abroad, Postings about Annual Summer Vacation to Nigeria (2 copies)
    - 1974, Pamphlet, National States Rights Party Most Important Program Details How to Ship Negroes Back to Africa, Drew L. Smith
    - 1975 Feb., Wilson Library Bulletin, Vol. 49, No. 6: Mollie Huston Lee: A Profile by Ray Nichols Moore, Bronx, N.Y.
    - 1976 Sept., Article 30, N.C. Leader Haley Traces Roots Back to Gambia, West Africa, by John Burhhem
    - 1977, 1979, and 1982, Clippings from the Durham Morning Herald
    - 1979 Feb. 11-13, Pamphlet, Symposium on Prospects and Needs in Historical Editing of Afro-American Materials, Durham, N.C., NCCU
    - 1980, Clippings from the Raleigh Times News and Observer
    - 1983 Sept. 21, Pamphlet, In Memoriam: Annette Lewis Phinazee, Durham, N.C., NCCU
    - 1983, Clippings from the Carolina Times
    - Undated, Flyer, FreedomCrafts of Mississippi
    - Undated, Pamphlet, The Booker T. Washington Memorial
    - Undated, Soul City 3 Year Plan, Soul City, N.C.
    - Undated, Memorabilia, Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) button
- Other Printed Material, 1934-1938, (2 folders)
  Published histories of black educational institutions.
  - 1934, Book, History of the Brick School, J.S. Inborden (Box 1)
  - 1937, Book, History of The Houston College for Negroes, I.B. Bryant
  - 1938, Pamphlet, History of the Louisville Municipal College for Negroes
- Artifacts and Photographs, 1833-1900, (1 folder)
  Six albumen studio portrait photographs, mounted on card stock, dating from the second half of the 19th century, along with a copper token from the American Colonization Society, dated 1833.
  - Albumen photographs, American Colonization Society token, 1833-1900 (Box 1)